Hello, today's דף daf is עז Ayin Zayin seventy-seven. We're in a
new פרק perek that has more geometry to it, as we saw
yesterday. We pick up in the משנה Mishna on the bottom of
עו עמוד ב, Ayin Vav Amud Bet, and we're dealing here now
with issues about how to combine two distinct courtyards. So we dealt
with the question of a window in the wall that gives them
the option of being one or being two and a circular window
and how do you fit essentially a square peg into a circle?
And now we pick up with some משנה. Mishna. כותל שבין שתי
חצרות kotel shebein shtei chatzerot bottom
of עו עמוד ב. Ayin Vav Amud Bet. כותל שבין שתי חצרות
גבוה עשרה ורוחב ארבעה. kotel shebein shtei chatzerot gavoha asara verochav arba.
So if you have a wall between two courtyards, it's ten high.
As soon as it's ten high and there's no appropriately sized window
or door, the courtyards are separate. There's no way they can become
they can be one עירוב eruv even if they want to. This
wall, however, is not just ten high, it's also four wide, which
makes it a רשות היחיד reshut hayachid four by four טפחים tefachim
wide. So therefore, and the question is the status of the wall.
The wall is now between two different courtyards. You can't carry from
one courtyard to the next. How about from a courtyard to the
wall? So the משנה Mishna says first of all, מערבין שנים ואין
מערבין אחד. m'arvin shenayim ve'ein m'arvin echad. The two courtyards have to
be separate. They can't be one. Again, that has nothing to do
with the width of the wall, just because there's a height of
ten and no legitimate window or door between them. But now getting
to the top of the wall: היו בראשו פירות. hayu berosho peirot.
Let's say there were fruit on top of the wall, really anything,
but fruit is just the scenario.
But there are fruit on top of the wall. אלו עולים מכאן
ואוכלים ואלו עולים מכאן ואוכלים. eilu olim mikan ve'ochlim ve'eilu olim mikan
ve'ochlim. Each side of the courtyard can use the top of the
wall, can eat the fruit on the top of the wall. The
top of the wall is its own רשות, reshus, it's a רשות
היחיד, reshut hayachid, so you can carry in any about you know
in any of the space on top of the wall for things
that already were on top of the wall.
A whole tree growing on? No, no.
Fruit. Separate fruit. Just like somebody left somebody left a שבת Shabbos
meal on top of the wall. Not not attached to it. Not
attached to a tree.
The basic point is the top of the wall is its own
רשות היחיד reshut hayachid and you can carry within its confines.
However, ובלבד שלא יורידו למטה. ubilvad shelo yaridu lemata. What they may
not do is carry from the wall to into any of the
individual courtyards to the two courtyards that it stands between because it
is a distinct רשות reshus and therefore you cannot carry from one
רשות reshus to the other. They haven't made an עירוב eruv together.
It's distinct from the רשות reshus of the courtyard and therefore you
cannot go from the top of the wall to either courtyard. פשיטא.
poshita. It's not so פשיטא poshita because there's also סוגיא sugya that
discusses it discusses what? Unless he wanted to include this כותל, kotel,
how would he?
You can't. If you can't combine the courtyards and the wall stands
between the courtyards, the כותל kotel becomes no-man's-land. Now the גמרא Gemara
will discuss scenarios where it might be more more connected to one
rather than the other and one of them will benefit from it.
But right now that they both have equal rights to it, or
they neither has sort of any particular rights to it, then you
cannot carry from it to the courtyard. Yes.
This wall is four טפחים tefachim wide? Yes. Are we understanding that
they have to eat the fruit sitting on top of the wall
or standing?
Yeah, if you want
to if you want to eat the fruit on top of the
wall then you have to stand in it.
It's a רשות היחיד reshut hayachid and eating over the... You can't
stand in your own רשות היחיד reshut hayachid and eat the wall
over the eat the fruit over the wall?
Oh, yeah. You can stand on it and lean over. You just
can't take the fruit back. Right. Exactly. Yeah. Okay. Now נפרץ הכותל
עד עשר אמות. nifratz hakotel ad eser amot.
Now getting back to the wall being a divider between the courtyards,
we discussed what the size of an opening is that allows them
to make an עירוב. eruv. Doesn't force them but allows them. They
could opt to be two or opt to be one. Now we're
getting to the other extreme. Not the minimum but the maximum. At
what stage can they not opt to be two? Is the wall
considered completely destroyed as it were and they have to be one?
So נפרץ הכותל עד עשר אמות. nifratz hakotel ad eser amot. If
there's a breach in the wall until עשר אמות, eser amot, about
fifteen feet, מערבין שנים ואם רצו מערבין אחד. m'arvin shenayim ve'im ratzu
m'arvin echad. That's like a door. So therefore they can do two,
they can do one. They have their option. מפני שהוא כפתח mipnei
shehu ke-petach because it's like a door. יותר מכאן, yoter mikan, if
the breach is more than עשר אמות eser amot or more, then
מערבין אחד ואין מערבין שנים. m'arvin echad ve'ein m'arvin shenayim. Then it
is no longer a wall and then they are considered one courtyard.
That idea of a עשר אמה eser ama opening destroying the wall
is very important because it gets to questions about in general like
can you know when you define walls around a רשות reshus to
make it a רשות היחיד, reshut hayachid, how big of a gap
can you have and that was dealt with in the first פרק
perek and you know I just want to mention to you there's
an opinion in the גמרא. Gemara. The רמב"ם Rambam rules that you
can't even have a צורת הפתח tzuras hapetach to close a gap
bigger than עשר אמות. eser amot. So all the עירובין eruvin we
use in the city are not like in any city is not
like the רמב"ם Rambam because according to the רמב"ם Rambam you would
need to make a צורת הפתח tzuras hapetach every fifteen feet. Okay.
So that's the idea. But that's not in the גמרא. Gemara. Here
it's in this משנה. Mishna. This משנה Mishna is just if it's
a big gap, it no longer it stops being a doorway and
it destroys the idea of the wall. Yes.
Center City
Philadelphia you mentioned according to the רמב"ם Rambam state according to the
רמב"ם Rambam they would have to... have had a lot of צורת
הפתח *tzuras hapesach*. Okay.
It took them a long time.
I could imagine. Let's see the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*. אין בו ארבע
אמות *ein bo arba amos*. Let's say the wall is not four
אמות *amos* wide and it's not its own רשות היחיד reshus hayachid
*reshus hayachid*. What's the story? So it's thin, it's whatever, it's ten
טפחים tefachim *tefachim* high,
normally we would sort of call it a מקום פטור makom patur
*makom patur*,
it's not four by four טפחים tefachim, *tefachim*. אמר רב אויר שתי
רשויות reshuyos, שולט בו לא יזיז בו אפילו מלא נימא *Amar Rav
avir shtei reshuyos sholet bo lo yaziz bo afilu malei nima*.
This is even worse because it's not four טפחים tefachim *tefachim* wide,
it's not its own domain. So it's this thin wall between two
courtyards. It's basically disputed territory. So each courtyard because it's not its
own domain, so it's שייך *shaiach* to courtyard A and to courtyard
B and they both are staking their claim on it. And therefore
you can't, nobody can carry in it. A can't carry in it
because it's also B's domain and B can't carry in it because
it's also A's domain and they haven't made an עירוב eiruv *eiruv*
together. Okay, so for he says you can't even carry a centimeter
in it because it is like carrying in this disputed domain. There's
no open, right. ורבי יוחנן אמר *Verabbi Yochanan amar*, now Rabbi Yochanan
says אלו מעלין מכאן ואוכלין ואלו מעלין מכאן ואוכלין *eilu maalin mikan
veochlin veeilu maalin mikan veochlin*. Actually
it's better.
Not only can you eat on top of it, but you can
actually bring food on top of it or the reverse, bring food
off of it to the bottom. That because it now is שייך
*shaiach* both to A and to B rather than being its own
domain, so therefore A can go from its courtyard to the wall
and vice versa and B can go from its courtyard to the
wall and vice versa. Okay, so everybody agrees on the phenomenon. This
wall is now connected both to A and to B. It's not
its own domain. According to one approach, that makes it disputed and
that makes it completely off limits even on the top of it.
You can't carry in it at all. And the other says no,
that actually makes it when A wants to use it it's part
of A and when B wants to use it it's part of
B. And even if it's happening at the same time.
How does that fit in different than the משנה Mishnah *mishna*?
Because in the משנה Mishna, *mishna* this is מעלין *maalin*, you can
bring food to the top of it. The משנה *mishna* said עולין
*olin*, that you could only carry on top of it. Here you
can even go from it to the courtyard and vice versa. And
that's what the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* just points out right now. תנן
*Tnan*, we taught in the משנה *mishna*, אלו עולין מכאן ואוכלין ואלו
עולין מכאן ואוכלין *eilu olin mikan veochlin veeilu olin mikan veochlin*. You
can go up to the wall and eat at the top of
the wall. עולין *Olin*, you can actually you can go up to
the wall. מעלין *Maalin* no, you can't bring food to the top
of the wall. So how is this different than the משנה *mishna*?
Why now it understands the משנה *mishna* you can't go bring on
and off the wall and according to Rabbi Yochanan you can. What's
the difference? And the answer's obvious as תוספות Tosafos *Tosafot* says and
doesn't understand the question. גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says לא הכי קאמר יש
בו ארבעה על ארבעה *lo hachi kaamar yesh bo arbaa al arbaa*,
if it's four by four טפחים tefachim *tefachim* and ten טפחים tefachim
*tefachim* high, so it's a רשות היחיד reshus hayachid *reshus hayachid*. It's
its own domain. It's separate from the courtyard. In that case עולין
אין מעלין לא *olin in maalin lo*, you can actually go up
to the wall, you can use the top of the wall but
you can't bring from the courtyard to the wall or vice versa
because it's a distinct domain from the courtyard. אין בו ארבעה על
ארבעה *ein bo
arbaa al arbaa*, when it doesn't have four by four, then מעלין
נמי *maalin nami*, then you can even bring from the courtyard to
the wall and from the wall to the courtyard. You can carry
on and off of the wall. Okay, so when it's not four
by four, it's not its own domain. According to רב *Rav* that
makes it completely off limits because it's competed territory, disputed territory. According
to Rabbi Yochanan it makes it connected to both and each courtyard
can actually bring, transfer from the courtyard to the wall and vice
versa. ואזדא רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan לטעמיה *Veazda Rabbi Yochanan letaamei*. Rabbi
Yochanan goes according to his reasoning. דכי אתא רב דימי אמר רבי
יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan, *Dechi ata Rav Dimi amar Rabbi Yochanan*, when Rav
Dimi came from ארץ ישראל *Eretz Yisrael* he said in the name
of Rabbi Yochanan: מקום שאין בו ארבעה על ארבעה *makom sheein bo
arbaa al arbaa*. If you have in it we're no longer talking
about courtyards. And this you might remember from our שבת Shabbos *Shabbos*
days. If you have in the middle of a רשות הרבים reshus
harabbim *reshus harabbim*, let's say you have a little platform that does
not have four by four טפחים tefachim *tefachim*, okay, so let's say
you have like a little, I don't know, a post office box.
Is post office box bigger than a foot by a foot?
Generally not. Okay, so you have a little platform standing in the
middle of the street that, or you have one of those little
boxes that have those free newspapers in them. You got a little
platform in the middle of רשות היחיד reshus hayachid. *reshus hayachid* that's
not, רשות הרבים reshus harabbim *reshus harabbim*
that's not four by four טפחים tefachim *tefachim*. מותר Mutar לבני רשות
הרבים reshus harabbim ולבני רשות היחיד reshus hayachid. לכתף עליו *mutar livnei
reshus harabbim velivnei reshus hayachid lekhatef alav*. That is a מקום פטור
makom patur *makom patur*, a no man's land. It's not its own
domain. Without being four by four it's not considered a domain by
itself. And therefore it is connected to any domain that is that
juxtaposes it. So if the people from רשות הרבים reshus harabbim *reshus
harabbim* can put something on it, they're not going to a different
domain. When they're using it, it's considered connected to רשות הרבים reshus
harabbim, *reshus harabbim*. And if it walks, it's if it's right alongside
a yard with a fence, you can go from your yard, from
your רשות היחיד reshus hayachid *reshus hayachid* and put on top of
it as well because when the רשות היחיד reshus hayachid, *reshus hayachid*
is using it, people of רשות היחיד reshus hayachid. *reshus hayachid* use
it, it's connected to רשות היחיד reshus hayachid. *reshus hayachid*. Okay, so
this is a not a distinct independent domain. It's connected to any
domain that is connected to it. And people from רשות הרבים reshus
harabbim *reshus harabbim* can use it and people from רשות היחיד reshus
hayachid, *reshus hayachid* can use it and not just on top of
it, but they can also
cross. Just like he says you can do, both courtyards can do
with the wall, and the fact that these two different domains are
both claiming stake to it does not create a problem. Actually, you
can have both. You can have your cake and eat it too.
רשות הרבים reshus harabbim can use it, רשות היחיד reshus hayachid can
use it. Courtyard A can use it, Courtyard B can use it.
It’s connected to both.
Okay, so ובלבד שלא יחליפו. uvilvad shelo yachlifu. The one thing you
can’t do is don’t put it, don’t from רשות הרבים reshus harabbim,
put onto this, on top of this box, on top of
this mailbox, and then the people from רשות היחיד reshus hayachid, take
from the mailbox, take that same thing and bring it into their
domain. Even if you did that, it would only be a rabbinic
problem, right? Because you didn’t go straight from רשות reshus, הרבים to
רשות היחיד. reshus hayachid But nevertheless, that’s already cheating. That already is
going to lead to go straight from רשות reshus. הרבים to רשות
היחיד. reshut hayachid Okay, but you see that it’s connected to both
and both can use it. So רבי יוחנן is very consistent. So
the גמרא Gemara says ורב לית ליה דרב דימי? verav leis lei
derav dimi? Does Rav not hold of Rav Dimi? This idea of
מקום פטור makom patur is something when we learn שבת Shabbos that
everybody agreed to. Everybody agreed that a מקום פטור makom patur can
be used both by the רשות היחיד reshut hayachid and the רשות
הרבים people. So if Rav agrees to it over there, why does
he argue about the wall? So the גמרא Gemara says אי ברשויות
דאורייתא הכי נמי. ei birshuyos deoraisa hachi nami. Look, when you’re dealing
there with biblical רשויות, רשות היחיד, רשות הרבים, there he’ll say you
have this no-man’s-land, it could be used by both. הכא במאי עסקינן
ברשויות דרבנן. hacha bamai askinan birshuyos derabbanan. Here we’re dealing with a
rabbinic issue, two courtyards which are both רשות היחיד. So the only
problem is an עירוב eiruv problem that they haven’t made an עירוב
eiruv. together. So that’s a rabbinic issue, right? Because they’re both a
רשות היחיד. It’s only a rabbinic issue of not having made an
עירוב. eiruv וחכמים עשו חיזוק לדבריהם יותר משל תורה. vechachamim asu chizuk
ledivreihem yoser mishel torah. And we have this sometimes, the rabbis sometimes
are even more stringent on rabbinic matters than on biblical matters. So
therefore maybe because you will say, eh, everything’s really רשות היחיד, it’s
only an עירוב eiruv. issue, we can be lenient. So sometimes they
want to particularly demand certain things in order so you don’t sort
of dismiss the importance or trivialize this whole system. So therefore
now תוספות Tosafos by the way points out it’s only specifically that
we’re being strict by עירובין Eiruvin הלכות halachos here. Now normally of
course הלכה כדברי המיקל בעירוב. halacha kedivrei hameikel beeiruv. Okay, that’s when
there’s a debate. But the idea that sometimes, it’s always that sort
of contradictory moves. It’s rabbinic, we’re being lenient, or particularly lenient by
עירוב. eiruv Oh my god, maybe we’re going overboard, we’re being too
lenient, so let’s make a particular requirement. So sometimes you have things.
What can I tell you? Fine, fine. So you sometimes do have
those contradictory moves. But the other thing that תוספות Tosafos points out
is that this idea of being strict about what’s essentially a מקום
פטור makom patur is only when the issue is an עירוב eiruv
issue. Two רשויות היחיד'ס reshuyos hayachids which haven’t made an עירוב eiruv
and a מקום פטור makom patur. between them. But he says if
you had another type of rabbinic רשות, let’s say you had a
כרמלית karmelis and a רשות הרבים and a מקום פטור makom patur.
in the middle. So he says כרמלית karmelis is also a rabbinic
רשות. He says no, there we’d be lenient as well. There you’re
dealing
with the heading of the topic is not עירובין. Eiruvin. The heading
of a topic there
is carrying, carrying from רשות היחיד to רשות הרבים or כרמלית. karmelis.
So anything that’s part of רשות היחיד, רשות הרבים, כרמלית, karmelis, all
of that is weighty and it’s in the ambit of the biblical
even if you’re dealing with a כרמלית, karmelis, and there we’re going
to be okay, we’re going to be cool with a מקום פטור.
makom patur But when you’re dealing with according to Rav, two רשויות
היחיד'ס reshuyos hayachids which really it’s all רשות היחיד and it’s just
an עירוב eiruv. issue, there we’re going to be stricter with a
מקום פטור. That’s just Rav. רבי יוחנן, as you’ve seen, is lenient
in both cases. A מקום פטור you can always go in both
directions regardless. You had a question?
Just by prohibiting something permitted, he’s not worried that he’s going to
drive people away? People, it’s making things so complicated.
Yeah, look, that’s been your general question about all of עירוב. eruv
What is the punishment here?
If somebody accidentally?
No punishment.
What’s your punishment? Is it considered חילול שבת?
chilul Shabbos? What? Is it considered חילול שבת? chilul Shabbos?
That’s an interesting question. There is a general discussion in the פוסקים
poskim whether violating דרבננ'ס derabbanan's is considered מחלל שבת. mechalel Shabbos. It
came up before when the גמרא Gemara dealt with the category of
מחלל שבת בפרהסיא. mechalel Shabbos befarhesia. And תוספות Tosafos raised the issue
about דרבננ'ס derabbanan's and תוספות Tosafot basing himself on רש"י Rashi says
it that could be that even by דרבננ'ס derabbanan's you’re considered מחלל
שבת. mechalel Shabbos. So somebody might be killed for? No, no, no,
no, no. That’s just for the label מחלל שבת. mechalel Shabbos. No.
First of all, how much would they enforce this stuff altogether? Normally,
like in theory? They would stone them down? Right, yeah, so in
theory they could do. Right, I understand. Look, okay, I understand.
Let’s move on. Okay, let’s move on. So the גמרא Gemara says
like this: אמר רבה אמר רבה בר רב הונא אמר רב נחמן
כותל שבין שתי חצרות צידו אחד גבוה עשרה טפחים וצידו אחד שוה
לארץ. amar Rabbah amar Rabbah bar Rav Huna amar Rav Nachman kosel
shebein shtei chatzeiros tziddo echad gavoha asara tefachim vetziddo echad shaveh la'aretz.
Now we... Dealt with the fact that this was, that when this
was a ten טפחים tefachim by four טפחים, tefachim it was its
own domain, and nobody could use it unless you made an עירוב
eruv. between the two courtyards. But what if this wall is more
connected to one courtyard than another?
Then we allow it to be considered the wall primarily of one
courtyard, okay? This wall of ten טפחים tefachim by four טפחים tefachim
between two. So if you have one scenario, let's say you've got
a wall here and it's standing between two courtyards. So basically here
is your wall and your courtyard, right? But on this side of
the courtyard the ground is a little bit higher, right, on this
side. So on this side of it the wall is actually more
accessible than on the other side, the top of the wall. So
since on this side the top of the wall is more accessible,
it's considered, the wall's considered part of this courtyard and therefore the
people of that courtyard can use it. Okay, this is the case
in the משנה where it's four טפחים tefachim wide and everybody agrees
that you can't go from the courtyard to the wall, but if
the wall is more connected to one courtyard you can. Okay?
Do they actually use it or does it make it different?
No, just the fact that it's more usable by that courtyard.
Do they use it more often? Apparently. Okay, so. So.
כותל שבין שתי חצרות, kotel shebein shtei chatzerot, צידו אחד גבוה עשרה
טפחים tzid echad gavoah asara tefachim on one side it's ten טפחים
tefachim high, וצידו אחד שוה לארץ utzid echad shaveh la'aretz
on one side it's leveled to the ground. Now it's not literally
leveled to the ground, then it wouldn't be even considered a wall
for that side, but it's closer to the ground. In that case,
נותנין אותו לזה ששוה לארץ notnin oto lazeh sheshaveh la'aretz you give
it to the side that it is closer to the ground משום
דהוי ליה לזה תשמישו בנחת ולזה תשמישו בקושי. mishum dehavi leh lezeh
tashmisho benachas ulezeh tashmisho bequshi.
This one it can use easily and that one it's more difficult,
so then it's considered the wall of one of the courtyards and
therefore in that case you actually can go from the courtyard to
the wall for that courtyard. Now, it would not be the same
presumably if it was twelve טפחים tefachim on one side and ten
טפחים tefachim on the other side. The point is that on one
of the sides it's not even high enough to be considered a
wall and therefore it is more connected to that courtyard.
וכולו לזה בנחת ולזה בקושי, vekulo leh debenchas ulezeh bequshi, anyone for
one it's easy to use and the other more difficult, נותנין אותו
לזה שתשמישו בנחת notnin oto lazeh shetashmisho benachas you give it to
the one that's more easy to use. In a similar way, אמר
שיזבי אמר רב נחמן, amar Shizbi amar Rav Nachman, חריץ שבין שתי
חצרות. charitz shebein shtei chatzerot. Let's say you have a ditch between
two courtyards. Now a ditch will also do the same effect of
a wall. If the ditch is ten טפחים tefachim deep, the courtyards
cannot make a unified עירוב. eiruv A ditch has the same effect
as a wall, they cannot be combined if it's ten טפחים Tefachim
deep. Although you have to ask, maybe it could be like a
פתח petach because you know just step over the ditch and so
on. But anyway, under these particular circumstances a ditch divides the courtyard
and similarly we're assuming that if the ditch is not only ten
טפחים Tefachim deep but four טפחים Tefachim wide, that that space at
the bottom of the ditch is a separate space, it's a רשות
היחיד and neither courtyard can use it. Same thing with a wall
except reverse. Okay? So let's say, however, that ditch is actually not
ten טפחים Tefachim, deep on one of the sides. One of the
ground levels is lower. צידו אחד עמוק עשרה tzid echad amok asara
from one of the sides it's ten טפחים Tefachim, deep, וצידו אחד
שוה לארץ vetzid echad shaveh la'aretz on the other side it's closer
to the ground. נותנין אותו לזה ששוה לארץ notnin oto lazeh sheshaveh
la'aretz you can use the bottom of the ditch, it's considered not
its own רשות היחיד but it's considered connected to the side that
it is closer to the ground, it is less than ten טפחים
Tefachim. deep from. משום דהוי ליה לזה תשמישו בנחת ולזה תשמישו בקושי
mishum dehavi leh lezeh tashmisho benachas ulezeh tashmisho bequshi etc., etc., because
one is easy, one is hard, and it's connected to the one
in which the use is easy. וצריכי vutrichi you have to tell
me both cases, the case of the wall and the case of
the ditch. אי אשמעינן כותל ee ashmian kotel if you had just
given me the case of the wall משום דבגובה משתמשי אינשי mishum
debegovah mishtamshi inchi because people actually use like heights, right? It's a
lot easier to use something that's you know a few inches or
a few feet off the ground. It's a lot harder to go
down to the bottom of a ditch and use something. So there
I could say that it's more usable and therefore it really is
part of at least one of the courtyards. אבל
חריץ
aval
charitz but a ditch בעומקא לא משתמשי אינשי be'omka lo mishtamshi inchi
nobody really uses ditches, you know, even if they're not so deep,
and therefore it's not connected even to the courtyard that it's not
so deep. אימא לא eima lo maybe it wouldn't be connected to
either courtyard. ואי אשמעינן בחריץ ve'ee ashmian becharitz if you told me
the ditch case משום דלא בעיתא תשמישא mishum delo be'isa tashmisha you're
not afraid to use it. You store something in a ditch, you're
not afraid somebody's going to come and steal it. It's more hidden.
Okay? אבל כותל aval kotel but putting something on top of a
wall דבעיתא תשמישא deba'ita tashmisha you're afraid to use it. אימא לא
eima lo maybe I would say that a wall is less considered
connected to the courtyard
because you know your objects are less protected. צריכא tzircha you have
to tell me both cases. Okay, fine. But the basic point being
that this wall which is no more, which is its own territory
when it's four טפחים Tefachim, ten by four, it could be considered
actually connected to one courtyard if from that side it is, it
is not just easier, it does seem that it's not enough of
a difference of. As I said, 12 and 11, but actually from
one side it's less than 10. And therefore not as much of
a full wall. Now the גמרא Gemara. continues. I should also mention
the following: there's an important debate you might remember in שבת Shabbat,
about what the הלכה Halacha is there. If I do have a
case of a wall that is, you know, less than 10 טפחים
Tefachim from this side and 10 טפחים Tefachim. from the other side,
is it considered a wall for, you know, for this area? Let's
say I've got a whole courtyard that's surrounded by a wall that
from the inside it's less than 10 טפחים Tefachim but from the
outside it's more. So in this case, תוספות Tosfos deals with that.
In this case you could assume even if הלכתית Halachically it's a
wall for the courtyard with the higher floor, nevertheless, because experientially it's
lower than 10 טפחים, Tefachim that makes it considered connected to that
courtyard. So that seems to be the point: easier to use and,
I would underscore, less than 10 טפחים, Tefachim then it is connected,
even if technically it's still a wall, it's connected to the courtyard
with which it is easier to use and lower than 10 טפחים.
Tefachim Okay, now the גמרא Gemara continues.
בא למעטו: Ba lema'ato: you want to lower the wall. You have
this wall between your courtyards and you want to use the top
of the wall. So now we've just got through saying that if
it's less than 10 טפחים, Tefachim. you can use it. So you
want to lower it. Now, how do you lower a wall? There's
two ways: you can either take off the top level, which is
a hard way, or the easier way the גמרא Gemara's says is
you raise the floor. Okay, so you are going to now build
some type of a mound at the bottom of the wall to
raise the floor and therefore to be able to use the wall.
אם יש במיעוטו ארבע: Im yesh bemi'uto arba:
if you have, if it's along the, here is your wall, okay,
and along the length of the wall this is four טפחים Tefachim,
wide, for, you have raised the floor for four טפחים. Tefachim So
at least for these four טפחים Tefachim. on the top of the
wall right here, opposite where you've raised the wall, it is, this
part of the wall is less than 10 טפחים Tefachim high. Okay,
and therefore this part of the wall is seen as accessible to
the courtyard. רש"י Rashi says it's like a פתח, Petach, accessible to
the courtyard and therefore connected to the courtyard. And if that's true
for a four טפח, Tefach, remember four טפח Tefach is considered like
the door and an opening, right? That makes the considered like the
whole wall is connected. It occurs to me that a way of
understanding this is you remember that we taught yesterday—and I don't know
where the eraser is, anyway—you remember that we taught
yesterday—it's behind your computer,
behind my
computer—you remember we taught yesterday that if you had a wall
that at the 10 טפח Tefach limit had a window that was
a little bit went into the 10 טפח, Tefach, then that was
considered to be a פתח, Petach, right? And so therefore effectively, therefore,
if you translate what that means is that would effectively be the
same as
since it's only 10 טפח Tefach that matters, right, it would effectively
be the same as a wall that looked like this. Right? Right?
Because that's the same as the window and this is four טפחים
Tefachim wide. So that's effectively what you are doing: you are making
a four טפח Tefach wide opening within the lower 10 טפח Tefach
and therefore by building your platform, by building your platform, because you
had a wall 10 טפח Tefach and you built a platform four
טפחים tefachim wide, so from the floor here till the top is
less than 10 טפחים. tefachim. So looked at another way, you've made
a situation like this. Okay? From this section it's less than, it's
less than 10 טפחים, tefachim, from the other sections it's more. And
therefore now you could discuss about whether that allows me to make
a פתח Petach between, you know, to combine the courtyards, but then
you'd have to say I did the same thing on the opposite
side. We are not concerned about what we were discussing before of
combining the courtyards, that was yesterday's discussion. We're concerned about using the
wall. So since this section is considered, you know, there's an opening
as it were and therefore the same, you know, and therefore this
section can be used by the people of courtyard A, it's considered
connected, it's considered access, as if this is an opening makes it
the same way when you had the, you know, the window between
the two courtyards that made the whole thing considered to be sort
of traversable. Here too, once this section is traversable it makes it
consider like you have access the whole wall is related to your
part.
Only four to 50, 50 אמה Amah long wall?
Yes,
the same way if you had a window or one door that
would make the whole wall considered accessible. This too makes the whole
wall considered.
It's only four טפחים tefachim, wide so it can only be a
פתח? Petach? Using the reasoning from,
yes,
it could be, right, it's all it has to do is get
it under 10 טפחים. tefachim. It does not matter like being 9.9,
right? Just high enough so that now it's less than 10 טפחים
tefachim from the top of the mound till the top of the
wall. Okay, so that's what it says. Let's go back to the
גמרא. Gemara אם יש במיעוטו ארבע, Im yesh bemi'uto arba,
if it's four טפחים tefachim wide, then מותר להשתמש בכל הכותל כולו,
Mutar lish-tamesh bekhol akotel kulo, you can use the whole wall. the
wall, you have access to the whole wall, and it's connected to
your courtyard. ואם לאו אין משתמש אלא כנגד המיעוט. ve'im lav ein
mishtamesh ela k'neged hamiut. But if it's less, if it's only two
טפחים tefachim wide, you can only use the section exactly opposite the
two טפחים. tefachim. So
the גמרא Gemara says, רב אשי, Rav Ashi, make up your mind.
אי הני מיעוטא בכולה כותל לשתמש, ei hanei miuta b'chulei kotel l'ishtamesh,
if for those two טפחים, tefachim? it's considered now that this wall
is connected to your courtyard, then if you could use those two
טפחים, tefachim. you could use the whole wall. אי לאו הני, ei
lav hanei, and if it's not wide enough to consider like it's
accessible, you know, so אפילו כנגד המיעוט נמי לא, afilu k'neged hamiut
nami lo, you shouldn't be able to use even the part directly
opposite where you removed it. So even for those two טפחים. tefachim
So אמר רבינא, amar Ravina, כגון שעקר חוליה מראשו. k'gon she'akar chulya
merosho. No, you did not build a mound. What you actually did
was you actually literally took a little section off of the top.
Okay, and therefore, if you took a little section off of the
top, somehow the גמרא's Gemara, saying in this case we can say
that this little section because it's not four טפחים tefachim is still
usable—so this section, I mean, on the one hand
because it's less than ten טפחים tefachim. it's usable, so that section
is connected to the courtyard, but because it's not four טפחים tefachim,
it doesn't make the whole wall considered accessible. It's not exactly clear
why the גמרא Gemara thinks that type of splitting makes more sense
to say you can use that section but it's limited to that
section when it's only two טפחים. tefachim Why not say the same
if I just built a platform that was only two טפחים? tefachim
רש"י, Rashi, you understand the point, we're trying to say this becomes
this, so why is it different? רש"י Rashi seems to say because
here the wall itself remains really ten טפחים. tefachim, You just have
access to it. So that's like a doorway as it were to
the wall. Okay, so either it is a doorway or it isn't
a doorway. You don't have a half doorway. Here, the wall actually
is lower in this section, so that section can be considered connected
to the courtyard without the rest of it being connected. Yes?
What if you built up a mound on both sides of the
wall?
We'll get to something like that, right, and then maybe you could
actually make one עירוב eruv between the courtyard.
Okay. אמר רב יצחק, amar Rav Yitzchak, כפה ספל ממעט, kafa sefel
mema'et, the same
way if you built a mound you could lower the wall, let's
say you just turned a basket upside down. Okay, you could also
use that. It's like a mound. Why not? Now, okay, it maybe
seems like why not, but the גמרא Gemara actually has a problem.
אמאי, amai, says the גמרא, Gemara why does that affect the halachic
status of the wall? דבר הניטל בשבת הוא, davar hanital b'Shabbat hu,
ודבר הניטל בשבת אינו ממעט. v'davar hanital b'Shabbat eino mema'et.
You could just take the basket away. So since that basket is
completely impermanent, you could even remove it on שבת, Shabbat. it doesn't
affect how we look at the wall. Sorry, what's the case? You
could put it... You had a wall twelve טפחים tefachim high, you
turned over a basket or a box, let's say you took a
soapbox as it were, okay, you know, or though you know those
like nice green sturdy plastic things, and you put it right by
the wall. And it was four טפחים tefachim wide, and you know,
it put... no,
by the bottom, so that that section is less than ten טפחים.
tefachim Now I have access to the wall, I can use the
wall on שבת. Shabbat Says no, you could just remove this box,
so it doesn't make the wall considered to be a different configuration.
It's not any... Okay, the fact that it could change on שבת
Shabbat. and you could just remove it. What if it was bolted
down? That would be different. So let's see what the גמרא Gemara
says. Okay. לא צריכא דחבריה בארעא. lo tzricha d'chavrei b'ara. The case
is where you connected it to the ground, like you pushed it
into the dirt. Like, okay, the edges were pushed down into the
dirt and therefore presumably you can't pull it out because it'll move
the dirt. So the גמרא Gemara says, דחבריה בארעא מאי הוי, d'chavrei
b'ara mai havei, who cares? You could still remove it. דהתניא, dehatanya,
we taught, פגיא שטמנה בתבן, pagia shetemana b'teven, if you took an
unripe fig and you put it in straw, straw being מוקצה muktzah
because it's not straw that's animal fodder, it's straw that's like for
cement mixing. So you have you put it in מוקצה muktzah straw.
או חררה שטמנה בגחלים, o charara shetemana b'gechalim, or you put a
wafer into embers that now have died down so there's no problem
about extinguishing them but it's מוקצה. muktzah. So you have something sort
of, you know, sort of buried in stuff that's מוקצה. muktzah. אם
מגולה מקצתה ניטלת בשבת. im megula miktzata nitalat b'Shabbat. If a little
bit is exposed, it can be moved on שבת. Shabbos You take
hold of the fig or of the wafer, you remove it. The
fact that incidentally you're moving the מוקצה muktzah stuff that's on top
of it is not a problem. That's called טלטול מן הצד, tiltul
min hatzad, you might remember that. Incidental movement of מוקצה, muktzah, particularly
when you are doing it for the sake of the non-מוקצה, non-muktzah,
and certainly when you're moving the non-מוקצה non-muktzah and everything else is
incidental, that is okay. So the same is true here. You remove
your box, you incidentally move some dirt. Who cares? Okay, it's just
like this case and still is movable. So the גמרא Gemara says,
הכא במאי עסקינן דאית ליה אוגנא. hacha b'mai askinan d'it lei ogna.
No, we're talking that this box has a lip, a lip at
the bottom. So therefore what happens if it's got a lip at
the bottom? It's not just the straight edges are stuck in the
ground and you a little bit move. There actually is—you stick it
in the ground and there's dirt over it. Okay. Here's your floor,
here's your box. It's not just those a little bit in so
that when you pull it out there's a little movement. Actually it's
got a lip on the bottom, so actually it's really like, you
know, it's like seriously connected because there's dirt on top of it.
And the גמרא Gemara understands that that type of a case, the
גמרא Gemara assumes would really be a problem of more serious like
moving. It's interesting the גמרא Gemara never considers that it's a problem
of סותר, Soter, that it's really considered really like a בנין Binyan
and you're really destroying it on שבת Shabbos. because you're not allowed
to change the configuration of the ground. But we'll see what the
גמרא Gemara will answer. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says וכי איתי
אוגנאי מאי הוי, V'chi isei ognayi mai havei, the גמרא Gemara still
assumes that all that does is it makes it more like you're
directly moving the dirt. Okay, who cares if that's what the concern
is? דתנן Detnan הטומן לפת וצנונות תחת הגפן, Hatomin lefet u’tznos tachas
hagefen, if somebody buried a turnip or a radish underneath of a
vine, בזמן שמקצת עלין מגולה, Bizman shemiktzas alin megulah, if some of
the leaves are exposed, אינו חושש לא משום כלאים ולא משום מעשר.
Eino choshesh lo mishum kilayim v'lo mishum ma'aser. First of all, this
is something that has been pulled off of the ground. So the
fact that you're now burying it in the dirt, even by the
way רש"י Rashi points out even if the leaves weren't exposed, the
fact that you're burying in the dirt is not does not make
it considered a replanting of the object. Now that's interesting. So that
means that if you if you bury it in the dirt near
a vine, it's not a problem of כלאים, Kilayim, or if you
bury it in the dirt and now it's a שמיטה Shmita year,
you don't start applying laws of שמיטה Shmita to it. Now some
types of things when you rebury them in the ground will start
taking root and regrowing, and תוספות Tosafot has that discussion. Does it
matter if certainly if it took root, it's a different story. We're
talking that it didn't take root. And we're also talking that the
purpose that you put it there was not to store it and
was not that it should continue growing. So therefore it's not considered
to be a planting and it's not a כלאים Kilayim problem and
it's not a שמיטה Shmita problem, ולא משום מעשר, V'lo mishum ma'aser,
and it's not ולא משום שביעית, V'lo mishum shevi'is, and if it
more grows you don't have to take more מעשר Ma'aser on it.
Okay, וניטלין בשבת. V'nitlin b'Shabbos. And רש"י Rashi says that's the only
reason we have to say leaves are exposed. A tiny little is
exposed, you can remove it on שבת. Shabbos. And that would be
a case where, see, you're doing a serious amount of moving of
dirt. By the way, according to some scenarios that the גמרא Gemara
talks about, it would even be if the radish is upside down.
Okay, and if the radish is upside down, you know, it's not
if the radish is right side up, right, you know, whatever, you
know, then the dirt more just collapses. But if it's upside down,
you're really disturbing the dirt around it. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara
says so look, that should be מותר here as well. Again, it
really gets to questions of are we talking about tight dirt or
loose dirt? Because if we're talking about tightly packed dirt, then besides
מוקצה, Muktza, you start wondering about why isn't it like חורש, Choresh,
right, why isn't it like you're digging a hole in the ground?
So anyway, so let's see what the גמרא Gemara effectively answers that.
גמרא Gemara says לא צריכא דבעי מרא וחצינא, Lo tzricha d'bei mara
v'chatzina, you need a hoe and a shovel. So this is a
case where it's really seriously buried and therefore you can't undo it.
To undo it would either be סותר Soter or חורש Choresh and
that's why. Okay, so that was just a... if it's just with
a lip then wouldn't do anything for the wall. So the basic
point here being that if you want to make the wall considered
lower so you can use the wall, you have to get it
has to be the configuration has to be something that can't change
on שבת. Shabbos. If you could easily remove what you had put
there to change the configuration, it's not considered to have to change,
you know, to have an impact on the halachic status. Let's take
a look now as we continue. even put in like a lengthy
platform? Presumably if you can just pick it up and move it.
But we'll see in a minute how the גמרא dealt with how
removable is removable. That's the next discussion. סולם המצרי, Sulam hamitzri, this
is not in the משנה, this is a continuation of the statement.
Said on the one hand you can overturn like a basket. Now
how about if you actually have a ladder next to the wall?
Does that make the wall considered to be lower and therefore usable
and therefore connected to your courtyard? So סולם המצרי אינו ממעט. Sulam
hamitzri eino memayet. If it's an Egyptian ladder, it doesn't help. הצורי
ממעט, Hatzuri memayet, one from צור Tzur from Tyre, that does. So
what does what's the difference? So גמרא says היכי דמי סולם המצרי,
Heichi dami sulam hamitzri, how are they what's a סולם המצרי, Sulam
hamitzri, an Egyptian ladder? אמרי דבי רבי ינאי, Amrei d'bei Rabbi Yannai,
כל שאין לו ארבעה חבקין. Kol she'ein lo arba chivakin. It's really
small, it's like a step ladder. It doesn't have four חבקין Chivakin
rungs. Okay, so it's a small step ladder, so that's like the
upturned basket, it's completely temporary, it does not change the configuration of
the wall. אמר ליה רב אחא בריה דרבא לרב אשי, Amar lei
Rav Acha brei d'Rava l'Rav Ashi, מאי טעמא דסולם המצרי דלא ממעט?
Mai ta'ama d'sulam hamitzri d'lo memayet? Why does it not lower the
wall? אמר ליה לא שמיע לך הא דאמר רב אחא בר אדא
אמר רב המנונא, Amar lei lo shamia lach had'amar Rav Acha bar
Adda amar Rav Hamnuna, didn't you hear what we just said on
the previous עמוד? Amud? אמר רב משום דהוי ליה דבר שניטל בשבת.
Amar Rav mishum d'havei lei davar she'nittal b'Shabbos. It's something that could
be removed on שבת. Shabbos, וכל דבר שניטל בשבת, V'chol davar she'nittal
b'Shabbos, if it can be removed on שבת, אינו ממעט, Eino memayet,
it doesn't lower the wall. So אי הכי אפילו צורי נמי. Ei
hachi afilu tzuri nami. So what? So you can also move a
bigger ladder. So it's all movable, so why should a bigger ladder
affect the configuration of the wall? So אנה התם קובעו קובעו. Ana
hosam kovo kovo. Okay, that, it’s not halachically, technically you can use
it, move it, but in practice it’s something that you leave there.
You got one of those big, you know, like roof ladders, right,
you know, you don't go ahead and easily just quickly fold it
up and move it around. So something that's big and heavy and
in practice you tend to leave where it is, that actually does
change the configuration. That actually does have halachic implications. So it's actually
interesting, it's not just theoretically movable. Even if it's theoretically movable, if
it's the type of thing that really is left there and has
a fixed location at least for a certain amount of time, that
would help and that would change the configuration of the wall. אמר
אביי: Amar Abaye: כותל שבין שתי חצרות, Kotel shebein shtei chatzeiros, גבוה
עשרה טפחים. gavoha asara tefachim. You have this wall, now we’re going
to talk about not making the wall lower than ten so you
can use it, but now we’re going to talk about effectively making
access on both sides. We’re going to turn this into a פתח
pesach and allow you to actually now make an עירוב eruv on
courtyards A and B together, okay? Until now we’re talking about courtyard
A using the wall because it's a little bit lower for courtyard
A. Now we’re talking about it being an opening on both sides
and A and B making an עירוב eruv. together. So כותל שבין
שתי חצרות, Kotel shebein shtei chatzeiros, גבוה עשרה טפחים. gavoha asara tefachim.
It’s ten טפחים, tefachim so you can’t make an עירוב. eruv. But
what did you do? והניח סולם רחב ארבעה מכאן וסולם רחב ארבעה
מכאן ואין בין זה לזה שלושה טפחים, v’hiniach sulam rachav arba’a mikan
v’sulam rachav arba’a mikan v’ein bein zeh l’zeh shlosha tefachim, ממעיט. m’mait.
So you put a ladder four טפחים tefachim. wide. Why does it
have to be four טפחים tefachim wide? Because what did we learn
about a window? What’s the minimum width of an opening to combine
the two courtyards? Four טפחים, tefachim right? So you put a ladder
four טפחים tefachim wide on this side. So you have half of
a window. You have half of a window because you’ve got a
window on this direction. It's not yet on the other direction, right?
Because the other direction is still ten טפחים tefachim high. Then you
put on the other direction, now I’m stuck because I can’t sort
of demonstrate, anyway, okay, that’ll just be the other side. Whatever, you
put it on the other side also. So now you’ve got a
window on both sides. But what happens if they’re on the other
side? Right, actually let’s try to draw it this way. Your side,
back that way, right. So let’s say though it's they’re separated from
each other. Okay? So if they’re within three of each other, three
is considered לבוד, lavud, that’s like they’re combined. And therefore it is
a window, you know, four טפחים tefachim, wide window that goes from
one side to the next, and then you can make one עירוב.
eruv. Even if each of those is two טפחים tefachim wide? Yes,
yes. No, the ladder has to be four טפחים. tefachim No, if
you say לבוד lavud you can't, no, you don't say לבוד lavud
to lengthen it, you just say לבוד lavud to say they're not
considered apart. It doesn't add to the width. Okay. But you just
say four טפחים tefachim has to be, the four, so that’s what
the גמרא said yesterday. Four טפחים tefachim. is considered the width of
an opening. לבוד Lavud is three טפחים tefachim. to consider that two
things are combined and not separate. But where did they say ואין
בין זה לזה שלושה טפחים? v’ein bein zeh l’zeh shlosha tefachim, Right,
why would they? No, because this is an opening, this is four
טפחים tefachim wide. It’s like a four, it's like a window, right?
So it’s like you have a window here, which is a good
window, and you had a window here, which is a good window.
But you have to combine the two windows. Okay? So this is
a window because it’s four טפחים, tefachim but things are not considered
combined unless they’re within three טפחים tefachim of one another. Is it
within three or not less than four? No, within three. That was
my question. No, this is a שיעור shiur of a window, three
is a שיעור shiur of being combined, okay? It’s three? Three. Correct,
it’s three, technically right. So within three, less than three. Okay, so
והניח סולם רחב ארבעה מכאן וסולם רחב ארבעה מכאן V’hiniach sulam rachav
arba’a mikan v’sulam rachav arba’a mikan ואין בין זה לזה שלושה טפחים,
v’ein
bein zeh l’zeh shlosha tefachim?
less than three, ממעיט. m’mait. Then it lowers the wall and not
only lowers the wall, it actually is a window and allows you
to make a single עירוב. eruv שלושה, Shlosha, if it’s more than
three, אינו ממעיט, eino m’mait, or three or more then it is
not a window on both sides and you cannot make and you
cannot combine the courtyards. ולא אמרו אלא דלא הוי כותל ארבעה. V’lo
amru ela d’lo hava kotel arba’a. אבל הוה כותל ארבעה, Aval hava
kotel arba’a, that’s only if the wall is less than four טפחים
tefachim wide. But if the wall is four טפחים tefachim wide, then
אפילו מופלג טובא נמי, afilu muflag tuva nami, even if they’re very
distant. Why? Because if you’ve got a nice wide wall here, you
know like in ירושלים, Yerushalayim, right? You can walk on top of
the wall, and the wall is four טפחים. Then even if something
is very distant over here, you have access. Because what do you
do? You walk to the top of the wall and then you
walk down and you go down like that. So the fact that
you can use the top of the wall to walk from one
to the next actually allows it to be considered as one opening
and therefore and therefore you can make one courtyard. Okay. אמר רב
ביבי בר אביי, Amar Rav Bibi bar Abaye, בנה איצטבא על גבי
איצטבא. bana itztava al gabei itztava. אמר רב ביבי בר אביי, Amar
Rav Bibi bar Abaye, בונה אצטבא אגבי אצטבא. boneh itztaba agabei itztaba.
You built a platform on a platform. אם יש באצטבא תחתונה ארבעה
ממעט. Im yesh be-itztaba tachtona arba'ah mema'et. Okay, so basically we're back
now not to making a פתח petach between two walls, we're back
now to you in courtyard A being able to use the wall
because you're making it less than ten טפחים. So you built a
platform. So we've been talking about building a platform, and we said
that if the platform is four, right, then that gives you access
to whatever, then it allows you to use the wall. Okay, so
but what you did is you did a platform on a platform.
You basically, you know, built let's say that and you had a
raised platform here and you built another one like that on top
of it. Okay, well if the bottom is big enough there's no
question, just ignore the top. The question is what if the bottom
is not big enough? אם יש באצטבא תחתונה ארבעה ממעט. Im yesh
be-itztaba tachtona arba'ah mema'et. So if the bottom one is big enough,
ignore the top one. You've basically lowered the wall because it's four
wide and it lowers the top from ten. אינמי, Inammi, אין בתחתונה
ארבעה ויש בעליונה ארבעה, ein be-tachtona arba'ah ve-yesh be-elyona arba'ah, this is
the חידוש. chiddush. The bottom one is not four, but the top
one is four. ואין בין זה לזה שלושה ממעט. Ve-ein bein zeh
le-zeh shelosha mema'et. So then it needs to be less than three.
If you've got a case that this is, I don't know, two
טפחים wide, the bottom, this is two טפחים wide, okay, and then
you have it built out like that, okay, and over here it's
four טפחים wide, so this should be able to be ממעט. mema'et.
The problem is what do you need for this not to be
considered a platform floating in air? It only lowers the top of
the wall if it's considered connected to the ground. So the only
way it's considered connected to the ground is if this is less
than three. If this is less than three then this platform is
connected to this and this is connected to the ground and the
platform's connected to the ground.
But if this is three or more, although this is four wide,
it's considered floating in air
and it does not lower the height of the wall. It doesn't
matter how high that bottom platform is? Yes. It's still considered connected
to the ground? Yes, because as long as it's within three, it's
connected to the bottom platform and then it's one extension of the
platform. Okay. ואמר רב נחמן אמר רבה בר אבוה, Ve-amar Rav Nachman
amar Rabbah bar Avuha, סולם ששלבותיו פורחות. sulam she-shlavotav porchot. If you
have a ladder that the rungs are flying. Now רש״י Rashi says
that basically means something that is not a, what do you call
a ladder that basically opens up and it's basically like a series
of steps? Right? You know you have that type of a thing?
Yes, like a step ladder. But those are things that actually what,
are combined. So רש״י Rashi says all פורחות porchot
means is that it's a normal ladder with rungs. תוספות Tosafot actually
says no.
תוספות Tosafot actually says it is a step ladder, but it just
means that the various platforms of the ladder are not connected. There's
air here between them. Okay, but it's a step ladder. That's how
תוספות understands it. What? That's most, well a lot of ladders are
rungs. This is a step ladder with steps. Okay, so it's a
step ladder. Okay. אם יש בשליבה תחתונה ארבעה ממעט. Im yesh bi-shliva
tachtona arba'ah mema'et. So now, we are, you put the step ladder
against your wall. Okay, and we are going to assume that from
the here till the ground, the bottom rung to the ground is
less than three. So it's considered connected to the ground. So if
this is four טפחים wide, this platform, then you've made a platform
four טפחים wide connected to the ground and it lowers the wall.
Is this a stationary or a removable ladder? That's a good point.
You've got to say it's not a removable ladder. Okay. ממעט. Mema'et.
אינמי Inammi or this is basically the same thing said by a
ladder. אין בשליבה תחתונה ארבעה. Ein bi-shliva tachtona arba'ah. The first step
is less than four wide. ויש בשליבה עליונה ארבעה. Ve-yesh bi-shliva elyona
arba'ah. And so this bottom step is only three wide and this
step here is four wide. It's essentially the same case. So this
step has to be connected to the ground. So this step will
be ממעט mema'et if it's connected. It's connected if it is less
than three away from the bottom step. ואין בין זה לזה שלושה
ממעט. Ve-ein bein zeh le-zeh shelosha mema'et. And then so if it's
less than three, it's connected to the ground and it lowers the
top and therefore the wall is considered accessible. So if it's on
one side you can use the wall. If it's on both sides
you actually would then be able to make an עירוב combining the
two. Okay.